Guide to the Elsa Guerdrum Allen papers, 1885-1976,
Allen, Elsa Guerdrum papers, 1885-1976
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Elsa Guerdrum Allen papers, 1885-1976, 1885-1968 (bulk)
21-18-1362
Allen, Elsa Guerdrum.
24 cubic ft.
Correspondence, diaries, pamphlets, manuscripts, photographs, and slides.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Papers consist of correspondence with family members and professional colleagues; diaries; photographs and research notes on early ornithologists; a bibliography of her Ph.D. thesis; travel literature; copies of grant applications (1960-1965); unpublished manuscripts. Family papers also include a genealogy of her Scandinavian ancestors. Papers are in English, Norwegian, and Swedish.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Ornithologist, lecturer, and writer, 1888-1969.
Cornell University Class of 1912, Ph.D. 1929.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Papers consist largely of research notes and manuscript materials for her book "The History of American Ornithology Before Audubon" published in 1951, her unpublished biographical study of the colonial naturalist, John Abbot, and other published and unpublished work on early ornithologists such as Mark Catesby and Alexander Wilson. Research includes correspondence with professional colleagues; photographs of early ornithologists and ornithological illustrations; pamphlets; travel literature; copies of grant applications; unpublished manuscripts for "The Story of Lalla," a novel with a Scandinavian background and "Minerva's Daughter," for which she sought publication by the Women's Press (1949) among others; a bibliography and manuscripts of her Ph.D. thesis on chipmunks; lecture notes and other materials relating to her work at Cornell University and the Laboratory of Ornithology. The collection also includes a color slide catalog of John Abbot's watercolors of birds and insects from collections in Europe and America arranged by bird species; a genealogy of John Abbot, with correspondence and photographs relating to the creation of an historic marker for him in Georgia. Biographical Materials include correspondence, much of it with family memebers; diaries (1912-1966); student notes, as well as family papers; photographs; and a genealogy of her Scandinavian ancestors which was used for "The Story of Lalla." The papers are in English, Norwegian, and Swedish.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Allen, Elsa Guerdrum.; Abbot, John, 1751-1840.; Allen, Arthur A. (Arthur Augustus), 1885-1964; Catesby, Mark, 1683-1749.; Wilson, Alexander, 1766-1813; Cornell University. Laboratory of Ornithology.
Subjects:
Ornithology.; Women -- Diaries.; Naturalists.; Ornithologists.; Women ornithologists.
Form and Genre Terms:
Bibliographies.; Biographies.; Genealogies.; Photographs.; Slides (photographs).
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Restricted to permission of Prudence Allen Bentley.
RELATED MATERIALS
See also the Arthur Augustus Allen papers, #21-18-1255, http://resolver.library.cornell.edu/cgi-bin/EADresolver?id=RMA01255.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Biographical Materials
Boxes 1-6, 21, 22, 25, 26
Family History
-Story of Lalla
-Allen Family and Arthur Allen Biography
Personal Journals
Personal Documents and Cornell University Student Materials
Personal Correspondence
General Personal
Personal Photographs
-Prints
-35mm slides
Series II. Professional Correspondence
Boxes 6-9
General
The History of American Ornithology Before Audubon
John Abbot of Georgia
-Alpha File
Alexander Wilson and Mark Catesby
Fellowships and Grants
Series III. Research and Manuscripts by Elsa Allen
Boxes 2, 3, 8, 10-19, 20, 23, 24, 26
Women's Issues
Chipmunk Study
Bird Poetry
Alexander Wilson
The History of American Ornitholgy Before Audubon
John Abbot of Georgia
Mark Catesby
General
Travel
Loose Notes and Bibliographic Cards
Miscellaneous
Series IV. Articles and Reprints
Box 20
Articles and Reprints by Elsa Allen
Articles and Reprints by Others
Series V. Professional Affiliations
Boxes 19, 20
Ornithological Organizations
Women's Issues
Cornell University and the Laboratory of Ornithology
Series VI. Photographic Materials and Illustrations
Boxes 21, 22, 25, 26, Mapcase
General
The History of American Ornithology Before Audubon
John Abbot of Georgia
-35mm Slides
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Biographical Materials
  - Family History
    - Guerdrum Ancestry, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Swedish Newspaper, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      In Swedish
    - Gjerdrum Family Legal Papers, 1848-1886 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Family Correspondence and Financial Papers, 1877-1902 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Some in Swedish
    - Family Correspondence and Financial Papers, 1878-1950 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Gjerdrum, Olaf - Legal and Financial Papers, 1880-1883 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Gjerdrum, Olaf, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Expenses: Legal and Financial Papers, 1895-1910 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - St. Cloud Florida Property and Notes for Story of Lalla, 1921-1924 and 1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Deed, Plans and Correspondence for House in Washington, D.C., 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Family Correspondence, 1879-1895 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Includes photos marked " Grandmother Karlsson" and "My mother's parents and 12 children"
    - Family Correspondence, 1880-1959 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Some written by Signe Bartsch. Includes Olaf Gjerdrum's Civil Service documents and a poem by Laura Gjerdrum
    - Family Correspondence, 1882-1956 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      "Letters to my mother" from Alexander Gjerdrum, my Uncle Otto and my Aunt Christina. Some in Swedish.
    - Gjerdrum, Laura - letters from her son George Guerdrum and from her Husband Olaf Gjerdrum, 1885 - 1956 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Gjerdrum, Laura, Signe Bartsch, Elin Kraemer - "Letters to my Mother", 1885-1956 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Includes photographs of Laura (Karlsson) Gjerdrum, Sophia Charlotta Berglaund (Laura's mother) and Laura's Sister Clara (also listed are Agnes and Maria)
    - Story of Lalla
      - Old Letters to Mother for Story of Lalla, 1864-1955 (Box 1, Folder 16)
        Includes newspaper clippings from 1922 in Danish
      - Box of Material Belonging to Laura Gjerdrum for "Story of Lalla", (1876) 1886-1926 (Box 1)
        Correspondence, Maps, Legal and Financial Papers
      - Bartsch, Signe Gjerdrum, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - From Jorgen Gjerdrum - Story of Lalla?, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Notes and Thoughts on the Story of Lalla, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 19)
        Notebook: Mainly written by Signe Bartsch. Correspondence in the pages.
      - Family History - some written by Signe Bartsch, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 19)
        Notebook
      - Notes, Correspondence and Research, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Translation off a Chapter about Elsa Allen's Grandfather, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Translation from Storebrand - First Chapter Regarding Jorgen Gjerdrum, Elsa Allen's Grandfather, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Picture Book of Stockholm, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - "Slektebok over en Fra Holsten Til Norge Indvandret Slekt" - Book about the Gjerdrum Family Genealogy, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 24)
        In Swedish or Danish
      - "Min Slakts Oden: En Kronika om Frander I Moderneled", 1930 (Box 1, Folder 25)
        Swedish Book
      - Booklets on Oscar and Helena Larson, 1943-1947 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - Notes on Sweden, 1940s (Box 1, Folder 27)
        Booklets in Swedish
      - "Vasteras" - book about the history of the Swedish town, c. 1952 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Story of Lalla - Handwritten, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
        Manuscript
      - Story of Lalla - Typewritten, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Allen Family and Arthur Allen Biography
      - Allen Children School Records, 1930-1937 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - McMillan Family History, 1935-1940 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - Clan McMillian Memories Newsletter and other ancestral notes, c. 1936-1940 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - Moore and Allen Family Trees, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 34)
        Note reads "To their children, grand-children, great-grandchildren"
      - Allen Family History (1), undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
      - Allen Family History (2), undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
      - Clan McMillan Materials, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - Arthur Allen Biography Materials and Chipmunk Study Article, 1943 and 1964 (Box 4, Folder 1)
        Arthur's Memorial Service and a copy of Animal Kingdom with Elsa Allen's Chipmunk Study
      - Memo from Cornell University Office of Public Relations, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - The Clan MacMillan Magazine and Correspondence, 1953-1966 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Correspondence and other Materials, 1955-1965 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Arthur Allen Memorial Endowment, 1964-1965 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - "The Curlew's Secret" for Arthur Allen's Biography, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Elsa Allen's Manuscript for Arthur Allen's Biography, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
        Includes a drawing of Arthur Allen by William Sargent
      - Drafts of Letters to James Perkins (not sent), undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Personal Journals
    - "Cornell" - Journal, 1912-1913 (Box 3)
    - "My First Journal", 1917 (Box 2)
    - School Notes, c. 1920 (Box 2)
      Some personal entries
    - Florida Journal - Book 1, 1924 (Box 2)
    - Florida Journal - Book 2, 1924 (Box 2)
    - Personal Diary, 1936 (Box 2)
    - Daily Journal, August 13, 1945-September 27, 1947 (Box 2)
    - Daily Journal, February 26, 1946-May 18, 1946 (Box 2)
      Cornell University - National Geographic Society Expedition
    - "Continued from the Journal of Cornell University - National Geographic Expedition February 26, 1946", May-June 1946 (Box 3)
    - Daily Journal, May 15, 1949-January 30, 1950 (Box 2)
      Diaries are written on one side and then flipped upside-down and the end and continued
    - Personal Journal, February - May 1950 (Box 2)
    - Daily Journal, May15, 1950-March 29, 1951 (Box 2)
      Includes journey to Europe with Arthur Allen and the Tenth International Ornithologists Congress in Uppsala Sweden June 10-17, 1950
    - Daily Journal, April 1, 1951-February 25, 1952 (Box 2)
    - Daily Journal, June 14, 1954-January 28, 1955 (Box 2)
    - Daily Journal, February 1, 1955-August 21, 1955 (Box 2)
    - Daily Journal, October 17, 1956-March 15, 1957 (Box 2)
    - Daily Journal, August 3, 1958-September 10, 1959 (Box 2)
    - Daily Journal, September 11, 1959-June 25, 1960 (Box 2)
    - Daily Book, 1959-1960 (Box 2)
      Includes some research notes
    - Swedish Journey, 1960 (Box 2)
      "Take to Sweden if possible 1967"
    - Daily Journal, January 29, 1961-September 24, 1965 (Box 2)
    - Journal, 1963 (Box 3)
      Very few entries
    - Daily Journal, January 2, 1964-May 5, 1965 (Box 2)
      Regarding Arthur Allen's Last Year
    - Daily Journal, 1965 (Box 2)
      Information on Arthur Allen from Alumni Office. Journal is mostly left empty.
    - Daily Journal, January 4, 1966-April 5, 1968 (Box 2)
    - Daily Journal, August 13, 1966-December 6, 1966 (Box 2)
      Writing about the fire that destroyed her home. Also notes on Mark Catesby and John Abbot
    - Address Book, undated (Box 2)
    - Address book and List of people, undated (Box 3)
      Guest list for 50th Anniversary Party?
    - Engagement Calendar, 1968 (Box 2)
      Mostly Empty
  - Personal Documents and Cornell University Student Materials
    - Passports, 1948, 1953 and 1960 (Box 3)
    - Allen Estate, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Pay stubs for work at the State of New York Conservation Grouse Station, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Bank Statements and Correspondence, 1935 and 1960s (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Travel Insurance, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Zoology Field Notebook, 1924 (Box 3)
    - Class Notebook, 1920-1924 (Box 3)
    - Zoology, 1925 (Box 3)
    - Notebooks for Fishes, Amphibians, and Mammals, 1920s (Box 3)
    - French Literature, October, 1947 (Box 3)
      Notebook: Loose pages of The History of American Ornithology Before Audubon tucked into the pages
    - "A Comparison of Racine's Phaedra with Euripides's Hippolytus, and Seneca's Phaedra" by Alice Dunbar, April, 1911 (Box 4, Folder 13)
      Submitted for the Corson-Browning Prize. Not Complete
    - "Dante Reports" Second Term 1911-1912, 1912 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Central High School and Cornell University - Studies and Alumni Materials, 1922-1968 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Zoology Notes - Fishes, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Zoology Notes - Mammals, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Cornell Examination Book: Zoology, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Class Notes, c. 1929 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Society of the Sigma Xi Correspondence, 1929 and 1965 (Box 4, Folder 20)
      Some Materials are confidential
    - History of Science Course, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 21)
      Notes and Texts
    - Alpha Omicron Pi Materials, c. 1921-1963 (Box 4, Folder 22)
      Oversize
  - Personal Correspondence
    - Allen, Arthur, 1912-1916 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Allen, Arthur, 1920-1922 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Allen, Arthur, 1923-1932 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Allen, Arthur and their children, 1933-1934 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Allen, Arthur and their children, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Allen, Arthur and their children, 1936-1944 (and undated) (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Allen, Arthur - Letters written by Arthur Allen on Elsa's behalf while she was in Europe, 1948-1949 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Allen, Arthur, 1948-1960 (and undated) (Box 4, Folder 30)
      Regarding Hudson Bay
    - Arthur and Elsa Allen's 50th Wedding Anniversary Party RSVPs, July-August 1963 (Box 4, Folder 31)
      Includes an original copy of Arthur and Elsa Allen's wedding invitation from 1913
    - Arthur and Elsa Allen's 50th Wedding Anniversary Party RSVPs, July-August 1963 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Cards and Letters for Arthur and Elsa Allen's 50th Wedding Anniversary and Party, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Allen, Arthur: Correspondence with the Lab of Ornithology after Arthur Allen's Death, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - Allen, Arthur: Letters of Condolence Received After Arthur Allen's Death, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Humorous Letter to Elsa Allen from Arthur Allen signed "A. Sapsucker", undated (Box 4, Folder 36)
      Note on folder "Helen Peterson's Party"
    - Allen Children, 1934 and 1935 and undated (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Allen Children, 1940-1949 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Allen Children and Grandchildren, 1951-1959 (and undated) (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Allen Children, 1960-1968 (and undated) (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Allen Children, 1963 and undated (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Dolly's Letter to Phoebe, August 27-September 3, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Allen Children - Schooling, 1933-1938 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Bartsch, Signe (Gjerdrum) - Sister, 1930-1939 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Bartsch, Signe (Gjerdrum) - Sister, 1940-1947 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Bartsch, Signe (Gjerdrum) - Sister, 1948-1949 (Box 4, Folder 46)
      Includes note about Carolina Parakeet
    - Bartsch, Signe (Gjerdrum) - Sister, 1950-1951 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - Bartsch, Signe (Gjerdrum) - Sister, 1952-1958 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Bartsch, Signe (Gjerdrum) - Sister, 1959-1965 (and undated) (Box 4, Folder 49)
      Also includes correspondence regarding Signe's illness
    - Bartsch, Signe (Gjerdrum) - Sister, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Elsa's letters to Signe
    - Bartsch, Signe (Gjerdrum) - Sister, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - "A Christmas Poem to My Sister" by Elsa Allen, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Dickson, Helen - Sister, c. 1927-1941, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Gjerdrum, Laura - Mother, c. 1916-1935 mostly undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Gjerdrum, Laura - Mother, c. 1935-1941 and undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Guerdrum, Geo. (Jorgen) - Brother, 1922-1957 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Kraemer, Elin - Aunt, 1918-1941 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Kraemer, Elin - Aunt, 1947-1949 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Kraemer, Elin - Aunt, 1950-1958 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Kraemer, Elin - Aunt - Regarding her aunt's illness and Estate, 1955-1958 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      Includes some correspondence with Signe Bartsch and Geo Guerdrum
    - Kraemer, Elin - Aunt, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Aunties Swedish Letters, 1956-1957 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      Found as is.
    - Kraemer, Elin (Aunt) - Will and Correspondence Regarding Memorial and Will, 1957-1959 (Box 5, Folder 14)
      oversized
    - Maddren, Milda (Elizabeth), c. 1938-1941 - mainly undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Wright, Anna (Allen) and Albert, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 16)
      Copy of a Letter from Louis Agassiz to Cornell's president Andrew D. White in 1867 - sent as a Christmas card.
    - Wright, Robert H., Captain, 1935-1938 (Box 5, Folder 17)
      Includes an article "An episode of the North Atlantic" by Wright
    - Letters from Norway and Sweden, 1937-1957 (Box 5, Folder 18)
      Includes a photograph of Elsa Allen
    - Letters from Home - Sweden and England, 1948-1949 (Box 5, Folder 19)
      Includes correspondence with Arthur Allen, Allen Children, Signe (Gjerdrum) Bartsch, British Museum, Elin Kraemer, Tompkins County Trust Company, H.F. & G. Witherby Ltd.
    - Letters from Home while in Europe, (1946) 1948-1949 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Cornell University Class of 1912 Reunion, 1957-1958 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - General Personal Correspondence, 1909-1919 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - General Personal Correspondence, 1920-1928 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - General Personal Correspondence, 1931-1939 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - General Personal Correspondence, 1940-1949 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - General Personal Correspondence, 1950-1959 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - General Personal Correspondence, 1960-1964 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - General Personal Correspondence, 1965-1967 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - General Personal Correspondence - Cards, c. 1960s (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - General Personal Correspondence, undated (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Telegraphs, 1931-1948, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Personal Business Correspondence, 1915-1968 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Personal Business Correspondence - Insurance, 1953-1966 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - General Personal
    - Pocket Bible (Box 3)
    - Peggy's Journal of the Children, 1924 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - News from Norway - During the War and Scandinavian Bulletins, 1944-1945, 1963-1965 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - French Notes, Labrador, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Vecko-Journalen - Swedish Newspaper and a Swedish Christmas Magazine - Stridsropet, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Programs for Events, c.1950-1968 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Party for Arthur Allen, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      Poetry, guest list and illustrations
    - Newspaper Clippings, c. 1949-1968 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Poetry by Elsa Allen, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - "Musings of an Ornithology Student" by Elsa Allen, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
      Poem
    - Ephemera, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
      Ribbon with small medal with an embossed ice skate and the letters W. S. K.; licenses; identification cards
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
      Printed Quotes from Edmund Burke and Russell; Letter Signed "An Old Maid"
    - Elsa Allen Memorial, February 02,1969 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Southwest Pacific and "Mrs. Allen's School for Genteel Females", undated (Box 6, Folder 54)
      Some humorous materials
    - Trial Will (for distribution of her possessions.), undated (Box 22)
      In same journal as ornithological notes
    - Prints from Dolly's first play - poem by Bell Sargeant, undated (Box 26, Folder 9)
      Oversized
    - The Nashville Tennessean Magazine, January 20, 1952 (Folder 2)
  - Personal Photographs
    - Prints
      - Family Photography Album (Box 21, Folder 1)
        Album
      - Gjerdrum, Olaf (Box 21, Folder 2)
      - Gjerdrum, Laura - Mother (Box 21, Folder 3)
      - Gjerdrum, Laura and house in Florida (Box 21, Folder 4)
      - Unidentified: Possibly Elsa's brothers and sisters before she was born (Box 21, Folder 5)
      - Sweden and Auntie's letters (Box 21, Folder 6)
      - Elin Kramer's Last Picture and ?ill Wooster Lalla (Clara?) (Box 21, Folder 7)
        Photographs found in folder regarding Aunt Elin Kramer
      - Kraemer, Elin (Peggy?) and baby (Box 21, Folder 8)
      - Family Photographs (Box 21, Folder 9)
        Most are labeled
      - Family Photographs (Box 21, Folder 10)
      - Laura Gjerdrum with the Allen Children and Arthur with Glen and Glennie (Box 21, Folder 11)
      - Kraemer, Elin photograph and correspondence (Box 21, Folder 12)
      - Other Swedish Relatives (Box 21, Folder 13)
      - Karlsson and Gjerdrum Family Portraits (Box 21, Folder 14)
      - "Mother's Children before my time, use in Story of Lalla" (Box 21, Folder 15)
      - Elsa Allen as a child (Box 26)
        In box with other glass plate negatives
      - Allen, Elsa (Guerdrum) as a young woman (Box 21, Folder 16)
      - Allen, Elsa photos used for passport (Box 21, Folder 17)
      - Allen Children (Box 21, Folder 18)
        Part of a letter on the back of the photographs
      - Allen Children (Box 21, Folder 19)
      - Unidentified Photographs (Box 21, Folder 20)
      - Unidentified Person (Box 21, Folder 21)
        Captain Robert H. Wright?
      - Guerdrum, Helene and Cornell Classmates, c.1912 (Box 21, Folder 22)
      - Cornell Class of 1912, Classmates, c. 1912 (Box 21, Folder 23)
      - Cornell Class of 1912, Reunion, c. 1922 (Box 21, Folder 24)
      - Cornell Class of 1912 - Reunion, c. 1950s and 1960s (Box 21, Folder 25)
        Includes a few color slides
      - Guerdrum, Helene for Story of Lalla, undated (Box 25, Folder 1)
      - Cornell Class of 1912, Classmates, undated (Box 26, Folder 1)
        Group portraits and pages from an album - Oversized
      - Misc. Personal Photographs, undated (Box 26, Folder 2)
        House, group portrait and portrait of Elsa Allen used for passport - Oversized
      - Elsa and Allen, Elsa at the John Abbot Memorial dedication and unidentified portrait, undated (Box 26, Folder 3)
      - England and Cambridge, undated (Box 21, Folder 26)
    - 35mm Slides
      - Austria - Grossglockner and Salzburg, undated (Box 21, Folder 27)
      - Austria - Salzburg and Zurich, undated (Box 21, Folder 28)
      - Zurich and Stein-on-Rhine, undated (Box 21, Folder 29)
      - Shoreham-by-Sea and Stockholm, undated (Box 21, Folder 30)
      - Switzerland and Austria, undated (Box 21, Folder 31)
      - Cambridge University, undated (Box 21, Folder 32)
      - Cambridge and London, undated (Box 21, Folder 33)
      - Norway, 1960 (Box 21, Folder 34)
      - Swedish cultural locations, undated (Box 21, Folder 35)
      - Loose Slide and Mr. and Mrs. Thorpe, undated (Box 21, Folder 36)
      - Dolly and Joe, 1954 (Box 21, Folder 37)
        Includes unlabeled landscapes
      - Arthur Allen Memorial in Sage Chapel at Cornell University, 1964 (Box 21, Folder 38)
- Series II. Professional Correspondence
  - General
    - A - Correspondence, 1935-1967 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia, 1935-1957 (Box 6, Folder 17)
      Mainly concerning Alexander Wilson research
    - Adams, Dr. Charles, 1931-1938 (Box 6, Folder 18)
      For Publication of Chipmunk Study by the New York State Museum. Includes a manuscript of the thesis.
    - Allen, Glover, 1937-1939 (Box 6, Folder 19)
      Museum of Comparative Zoology, Cambridge, MA regarding articles in the Auk
    - American Association of University Women, 1933-1937 (1950) (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - American Philosophical Society, 1933-1953 (Box 6, Folder 21)
      Includes correspondence regarding publication of book as well as Plans of Study and other grant materials
    - American Philosophical Society, 1936-1961 (Box 6, Folder 22)